# Taewan Kim PhD Student

Department of Industrial Design, KAIST Bldg. N25, 291 Daehak-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 34141, Republic of Korea taewan@kaist.ac.kr | https://taewankim.io

#### **Research Interests**

Human-computer Interaction, User Experience Research, Human-centered Design, Human-ai interaction, Mental Well-being, Social Computing

As an HCI researcher with a background in industrial design, my primary research focuses on designing everyday Human-ai Interactions (HAI) with a Human-centered design approach. Currently, I am working on investigating the design of HAI in the Mental-wellbeing domain. Recently, I investigated exploiting prediction algorithms and explainability that facilitate self-reflection for the mental-wellbeing (Accepted to CHI 2022). I also developed a social bot displaying depressive symptoms and disclosing vulnerable experiences to investigate the role of virtual agents as care receivers for mental health (Accepted to CHI 2020).

Based on my strength in qualitative user research and human-centered design, I create artifacts, methodologies, and frameworks to inspire meaningful and positive algorithmic experiences for HCI researchers and practitioners.

#### Education

Sep. 2021 - 2023 (EST) KAIST, Department of Industrial Design

Ph.D. student

Adviser: Prof. Hwajung Hong

Sep. 2018 - Aug. 2021 Seoul National University, Interdisciplinary Program in Cognitive Science

Ph.D. Candidate (\*Transferred to KAIST)

Adviser: Prof. Hwajung Hong

Mar. 2016 - Feb. 2018 Ulsan National Institute of Science and Technology, School of Creative Design Engineering

M.E. in Creative Design Engineering

Dissertation: Helping Friends Suffering Mental Health Issues: Challenges and Opportunities for Social

support on Social Media from the Peer's Point of View

Adviser: Prof. Hwajung Hong

Sep. 2011 - Feb. 2016 Handong University, Department of Industrial Design

B.S in Product Design (Cum laude)

# **Experiences**

Sep. 2019 - Dec. 2019 Undergraduate Teaching Assistant | Seoul National University

2114.409 Creative Research Practice

Apr. 2018 - Mar. 2019 Assistant Researcher | Institute of Communication Research, Seoul National University

## **Publications**

Conference papers

Journal articles Taewan Kim, Haesoo Kim, Hayeon Lee, Hwarang Goh, Shakhboz Abdigapporov, Mingon Jeong,

Hyunsung Cho, Kyungsik Han, Youngtae Noh, Sung-Ju Lee and Hwajung Hong. "Prediction for Retrospection: Integrating Algorithmic Stress Prediction into Personal Informatics Systems for College Students' Mental Health" *Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing* 

Systems. 2022. (forthcoming)

Mintra Ruensuk, **Taewan Kim**, Hwajung Hong, and Ian Oakley. "Sad or just jealous? Using Experience Sampling to Understand and Detect Negative Affective Experiences on Instagram" *Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2022. (forthcoming)

Jennifer G. Kim, **Taewan Kim**, Sungin Kim, Soyeon Jang, Stephanie Lee, Heejung Yoo, Kyungsik Han, and Hwajung Hong. "The Workplace Playbook VR: Exploring the Design Space of Virtual Reality to Foster Understanding and Support of Autistic People in the Workplace" *Proceedings of the Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. CSCW 2022* (forthcoming)

**Taewan Kim**, and Hwajung Hong. "Understanding University Students' Experiences, Perceptions, and Attitudes Toward Peers Displaying Mental Health-related Problems on Social Network Sites: Online Survey and Interview Study" *Journal of Medical Internet Research - Mental Health* (2021)

**Taewan Kim**, Mintra Ruensuk, and Hwajung Hong. "In Helping a Vulnerable Bot, You Help Yourself: Designing a Social Bot as a Care-Receiver to Promote Mental Health and Reduce Stigma." *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2020.

**Taewan Kim**, James A. Self, and Hwajung Hong. "Design Constraints and Their Influence upon Design Outcome." *Archives of Design Research* 31.4 (2018): 23-41.

#### Poster / Workshop

Youjin Hwang, **Taewan Kim**, Junhan Kim, Joonhwan Lee, and Hwajung Hong. "Leveraging challenges of an algorithm-based symptom checker on user trust through explainable AI" *ACM CHI2021* Workshop on Realizing AI in Healthcare: Challenges Appearing in the Wild. 2021

**Taewan Kim**, Youjin Hwang, Junhan Kim, Joonhwan Lee, and Hwajung Hong. "질병의 자가 진단을 위한 알고리즘 기반 증상 확인 애플리케이션의 사용자 경험에 관한 탐색적 연구 (An exploratory study on the algorithm user experience of a symptom checker application for self-diagnosis" *The Proceedings of HCI KOREA 2021*. 2021

**Taewan Kim,** and Hwajung Hong. "Studying Students Experiencing Mental Health Problems" *ACM CSCW 2018 Workshop on Conducting Research with Stigmatized Populations*. 2018

**Taewan Kim**, Young-Woo Park, and Hwajung Hong. "Calm Station: An Interactive Perpetual Desk Object that Reduces Digital Distractions." *Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference Companion Publication on Designing Interactive Systems*. 2017.

Kang, Mingu, **Taewan Kim**, Ahn, Junghwan, and Kim, Youngjae. "FamCom: A Communication Service Enhancing Conversation Quality Between Elders Residing in Care Hospital and Their Family Member." *Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2015.

### **Awards**

2015	Student Design Competition, Top4   ACM CHI 2015
2015	UNIST Creative Design and Engineering Competition, Silver   UNIST
2014	Undergraduate Research Competition, Second Place   Handong Univ.
2014	Samsung Tomorrow Solution Award, Excellence award   SAMSUNG

## **Skills**

## User Research, Qualitative Analysis

Interviewing, Conducting surveys, Field research, Contextual Inquiry Grounded theory, Thematic analysis

#### UX/UI Design, Fabrication

2D graphic and interface design: Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop, Premiere, Sketch, Figma 3D modeling and fabrication: SIEMENS NX, Rhino, AutoCAD, 3D Printing, Laser cutting, Arduino

# **Patents**

# Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation Plate for a First-aid Treatment

Korea Patent No. 10-1628073

AR simulator

Korea Design Protection No. 30-0938066

# **Academic Societies and Services**

**Peer Reviewing** ACM TEI 2018 Paper IASDR 2021 Paper